Taft, Philip Papers 5541
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Philip Taft Papers
1836-1981
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Taft, Philip
5541
16.67 cubic feet
16.7 linear ft.
Papers (documents).
Subject files and research notes, which Philip Taft gathered in preparation of his book manuscripts. Included are numerous original documents, which are interspersed throughout the research notes. Particularly well documented subjects are: organized labor abroad; the AFL-CIO's position on foreign affairs; maritime unions; labor and the National Industrial Recovery Act; labor and the National Labor Relations Board; racketeering; labor and the steel industry; teachers' unions; and the two World Wars.
3121255
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
ce/cb, January 12, 2006
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, May 30, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Philip Taft was one of the nation's foremost historians of the American labor movement, especially the American Federation of Labor. He wrote 14 books and more than 82 articles and was recognized by scholars and trade union leaders as a chief source on the growth of American labor.
Born March 22, 1902 in Syracuse, NY, Taft dropped out of school in the sixth grade and worked as an errand boy, a field and factory worker, a coal passer on ore boats in the Great Lakes and a pipe liner in the oil fields of Kansas. He completed high school at night and entered the University of Wisconsin at the age of 26 in 1928. He was co-author with his teacher, Selig Perlman, of the fourth volume of "History of Labor in the United States," which appeared in 1935 when he received his doctorate. He worked for the Wisconsin Industrial Commission, the Resettlement Administration and the Social Security Administration before joining the Brown faculty in 1937. He was chairman of the economics department in 1949-1953 while writing such volumes as "Economics and Problems of Labor" (1942), the chapter on the growth of union membership under the New Deal in the Twentieth Century Fund's "How Collective Bargaining Works" and "Movements for Economic Reform" (1950). A member of the Brown University faculty for 31 years, Dr. Taft retired in 1968. He did not give up his research and in 1975 was awarded a Guggenheim fellowship to continue studying the history of the labor movement in Alabama.
Among many renowned works, Philip Taft is the author of "The A.F. Of L. in the Time of Gompers" (New York, Harper [1957]); "Corruption and Racketeering in the Labor Movement" (Ithaca [New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations, Cornell University, 1970]); "Economics and Problems of Labor" (Harrisburg, Pa., Stackpole sons [c1942]); "History of Labour in the United States" (New York, Macmillan, 1918-35), with John Commons and others; and "United They Teach; The Story of the United Federation of Teachers" (Los Angeles, Nash Pub. [1974]).
Philip Taft died in Providence, RI on November 17, 1976 at the age of 74.
Scope and Contents
The Philip Taft Papers span the years 1840-1976 and occupy 16 linear feet. The collection consists mainly of subject files and research notes, which Philip Taft gathered in preparation of his book manuscripts. Of note are the numerous original documents, which are interspersed throughout the research notes. Among the particularly well documented subjects are: organized labor abroad; the AFL-CIO's position on foreign affairs; maritime unions; labor and the National Industrial Recovery Act; labor and the National Labor Relations Board; racketeering; labor and the steel industry; teachers' unions; and the two World Wars. The files are organized in alphabetical order.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5142: Glass Bottle Blower's Association of the United States and Canada Records 5402 mf: Correspondence of American Federation of Labor President William Green on Microfilm 5527 mf: National AFL Conventions on Microfilm
Arrangement
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Research/Subject Files
Series III. PUBLICATIONS (PUBLISHED AND UNPUBLISHED MANUSCRIPTS)
Series IV. IMPARTIAL UMPIRE DECISIONS OF AFL-CIO INTERNAL DISPUTES PLAN
Series V. LECTURE NOTES
Series VI. MISCELLANEOUS
Industrial relations -- United States -- History -- Sources; Labor unions -- United States -- History -- Sources; Acheson, Dean. 1893-1971.; Beddoe, Noel; Bierne, Joseph; Brown, Irving, 1911-; Cogen, Charles, 1903-; Curran, Joseph Edwin, 1906-1981; Davis, John P. (John Preston), 1905-1973; Dewey, Thomas E. (Thomas Edmund), 1902-1971.; Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982; Fulbright, J. William (James William), 1905-1995; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924; Green, William, 1870-1952; Harriman, W. Averell (William Averell), 1891-1986; La Guardia, Fiorello H. (Fiorello Henry), 1882-1947; Linville, Henry R. (Henry Richardson), 1866-1941; Lovestone, Jay; Lye, Trygvie; Meany, George, 1894-1980; Murray, Philip, 1886-1952; Pressman, Lee, 1906-1969; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945; Rutz, Henry J.; Shanker, Albert; Simonson, Rebecca; Taft, Philip, 1902-; Taft, William Howard, 1857-1930; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972; Watt, Robert; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924; Woll, Matthew, 1880-1956; AFL-CIO; African-American Labor Center; Amalgamated Association of Iron, Steel, and Tin Workers; American Federation of Labor. Executive Council; American Institute for Free Labor Development; American Merchant Marine Institute; Asian-American Free Labor Institute; Association of American Shipowners; Communist Party of the United States of America; Conference of Maritime Unions; Council on Foreign Relations; Food, Tobacco, Agricultural and Allied Workers Union of America; International Fur and Leather Workers Union of the United States and Canada; International Labour Organisation; International Longshoremen's and Warehousemen's Union; International Longshoremen's Association; International Longshoremen's Association. Pacific Coast District; International Trade Union Conference; International Union of Mine, Mill, and Smelter Workers; International Union, United Automobile, Aircraft, and Agricultural Implement Workers of America; National Maritime Union of America; National Union of Marine Cooks and Stewards; New York (N.Y.). Board of Education; ORIT (Organization); United Federation of Teachers; United Office and Professional Workers of America; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Merchant Marine and Fisheries; United States. National Labor Relations Board; Boston Naval Shipyard (Boston, Mass.); United Steelworkers of America
3121255
- Series I. Correspondence
  - American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 1949-1976 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Routine
  - American Arbitration Association, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  - American Association of University Professors, 1958-1968 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
    Re activities as member of AAUP Council and routine
  - American Philosophical Society, 1954-1962 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Re Penrose Foundation Grant resulting in research for the books The Structure and Government of Labor Unions by Taft and The American Federation of Labor from the Death of Gompers to the Merger by Taft. Abstract and galleys for manuscript "Labor History and the Labor Issues of Today," 1 page, and routine
  - American Society of Real Estate Counselors, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Re conference of American Society of Real Estate Counselors and routine
  - An-Ar, 1965-1975 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Re abstract of manuscript entitled "Violence in American Labor Disputes" by Taft, 2 pages. Re research done for Arno Press, Inc. and routine
  - Ba-Bel, 1961-1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bernstein Project (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Re activities of Board of Directors
  - Bl-Bo, 1965-1976 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brazier, Richard. Letters to and Theresa Taft, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Includes personal letters from Brazier (1967-1969) to and Theresa Taft of Providence, Rhode Island and Amherst, New York, which express his thoughts on the following: rebellion in Nigeria, wobblies, Montreal, death of Edith Chaplin, Ben Fletcher (black organizer), Medicare and Medicaid, Mao/Maoism, Gurlet Flynn, Spokane Free Speech Fight, Scottish history, Joe Hill, Little Red Songbook (wobbly songbook), students, blacks and Puerto Ricans, Bill Haywood, John Panzner (charter member of the I.W.W.), the "Twelve Apostles", Communism, Louis Moreau and others. Includes typed manuscripts of poems by Brazier, some written while a prisoner at Leavenworth. Some subjects reflected in the poems are prisons, the Spokane Free Speech Fight, doom, wobblies, Joe Hill, the Centralia case (Armistice Day tragedy at Centralia, Washington, 1919), and Bill Haywood. Includes an article reprinted from Labor History, Volume 7, Number 2, Spring 1966, entitled "The Mass I.W.W. Trial of 1918: A Retrospect" by Brazier, only surviving member of the General Executive Board of the Industrial Workers of the World (I.W.W.) who served with William D. Haywood at the time of the whole-sale arrests of World War I. The following figures and topics appear in the article: charge of conspiracy, Judge Kenesaw Mountain Landis, prosecuting attorneys Frank K. Nebeker and Claude R. Porter, I.W.W. chief counsel George Vanderveer, "The Report of the Industrial Relations Commission", prison conditions, and I.W.W. members Jim Thompson, Ralph Chaplin, John Foss, and Bill Haywood
  - Bri-Bru, 1957-1966 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Buffalo-Bur, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Re Taft's time spent at the University of Buffalo, and routine
  - Cai-California, 1955-1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Re time spent at University of California in both Berkeley and Davis; pages 20-155 plus of untitled manuscript by Taft, and routine
  - Carm-Deane Carson, 1961-1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Re essay contribution to volume compiled by U.S. Small Business Administration entitled The Vital Majority: Small Business in the American Economy. Manuscript for essay "Labor Management Problems and Relations in Small Business" by Taft, 28 pages. Draft of essay, "The Social Responsibility of Banks: A Minority Report" by Deane Carson, 36 pages; and routine
  - Ce-Ch, 1958-1971 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Cog-Con, 1948-1976 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Review of book, Jewish Labor in the USA (by Melech Epstein) by Taft; letter from Committee for Democratic Unionism (Charles Rodrigues); correspondence with Charles Cogen, President AFT re Taft manuscript; and routine
  - Cook, Alice, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Includes some student term papers and routine
  - Cornell University-Cors, 1962-1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cr-Cu, 1957-1970 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Da-Department of Employment Security, 1965-1975 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Includes State of Rhode Island and Providence Plantations Purchase Orders for Taft re Solvency Study of Employment Security Fund, and routine
  - Der-Dictionary of American Biography, 1960-1975 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Includes untitled manuscript about James Hudson Maurer by Taft, 2 copies, 3 pages each; untitled manuscript about Philip Murray by Taft, 8 pages; list of Philip Murray records with CIO in Washington, D.C.
  - Do-Du, 1963-1975 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - E, 1963-1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Fa-Fe, 1956-1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Finch, Herbert, LMDC, Cornell University, 1972-1976 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    Re donation of various papers to the Cornell University Library System and routine
  - Ford Foundation Grant, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 27-28)
    Including 2 grant proposals re the effect of federal labor legislation upon union administration and collective bargaining, 13 pages and 18 pages, by Taft and Philip Ross; a grant proposal re the effect of the National Labor Relations and the Labor Management Reporting and Disclosure Acts upon the administration and management of labor unions and of collective bargaining, 6 pages, by Taft and Philip Ross; and routine
  - Ford Foundation - Older Worker Project, 1952-1962 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Fr, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Includes brief biography entitled "Labor History's Phil Taft" by Nelson Frank, 7 pages, and routine
  - Fund for the Republic Trade Union Project, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Ga-Gr, 1961-1975 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Includes research proposal by Stanley B. Greenberg entitled "Race and Modernization," 15 pages and routine
  - Greenwood Press, 1969-1978 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    Manuscript - Introduction for reprint of Party Organizer, 1968, by Taft, 8 pages; index from Right of Union Members and the Government by Taft, 20 pages, and routine
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1957-1976 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    Includes Taft's application for a Guggenheim Grant with related correspondence and routine
  - Gugm-Ha, 1963-1974 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Harper and Row (Publishers), 1965-1972 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Includes royalty statements and routine
  - Harper and Row - Contracts and Statements, 1956-1964 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Harper and Row - General Correspondence, 1956-1966 (Box 1, Folder 38-40)
    Includes preface and dedication to The AFL in the Time of Gompers by Taft, 6 pages; various commentary on Taft's books; introduction to Organized Labor in American History by Taft, 13 pages, 2 copies; abstract of The American Federation of Labor in the Time of Gompers by Taft, 2 pages; and routine
  - Harvard University, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 40a)
  - Harvard University Press, 1949-1968 (Box 1, Folder 41-43)
    Re research for study on appellate procedure in union organizations; jacket, front and back flap copy for Labor Politics American Style by Philip Taft; readers report on Studies in the Structure and Government of Labor Union by Philip Taft, and routine
  - Hawaii, University of, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    Re summer 1962 Guest Faculty Position and routine
  - He-Hu, 1961-1974 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    Includes reprint of a summary of a doctoral dissertation, John Sidney: The Pioneer in American Industrial Unionism and Industrial Government by Charles Edward Killeen, 4 pages, and routine
  - Il-In, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    Untitled essay about union mergers by Taft, 12 pages, done for the 25th Anniversary of the Industrial Relations Research Association (IRRA) (1973), entitled "The Next 25 Years of Industrial Relations" and routine
  - International Encyclopedia of Social Services, 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Preliminary "Table of Contents and Directory of Contributors" for the International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, published by the Macmillan Company, 36 pages, and an untitled booklet describing the International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, 40 pages
  - Ir-Iv, 1962-1976 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - J, 1961-1975 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - K, 1957-1973 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    Personal and routine
  - La, 1964-1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Labor History - Milton Cantor, 1965-1976 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Landrum-Griffin Law - People to Thank A-F, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Re data collection for study of Landrum-Griffin by Taft, and routine
  - Landrum Griffin Law - People to Thank G-R, 1962-1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    cont.
  - Landrum Griffin Law - People to Thank S-W, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Le, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Library Press and Nash Publications, 1972-1976 (Box 2, Folder 8-11)
    Correspondence re publication of Defending Freedom: American Labor and Foreign Affairs by Taft; November 1, 1973 letter from George Meany, 1 page; copy of the AIFLD Report, December 1973, 6 pages; introduction to Defending Freedom ... by Robert Murphy, 3 pages; brief untitled essay about George Meany's impact on foreign affairs, no author given, 4 pages; and routine
  - Li-Lo, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    Letter to Taft from Frank Licht, former Governor of Rhode Island, and routine
  - Lovestone, Jay-Lu, 1965-1975 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    Letter from George Meany, dated November 1, 1971, 1 page, and routine
  - Ma-Me, 1940-1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Michigan University - Jack Stuber, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Michigan University - Project, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Re studies of various unions and routine
  - Mi-Mo, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Na-Nat, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Nash Publishing - German Translation, 1973-1976 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    Includes description of Defending Freedom by Taft in German, 3 pages; some correspondence in German; and routine
  - Nea-New, 1949-1971 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Essay on political situation in Rhode Island by Taft, untitled, 4 pages; letter submitted by Taft to the editor of the New York Times, dated December 17, 1964 and routine
  - New York University Law Review-No, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Old Age Project, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
    Re study of employment of older workers, includes index of films by location that gives name, address, U.P. and number of employees, 72 pages
  - O-Oz, 1960-1972 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Letter to Christopher Evans from Terence Powderly re Order of Knights of Labor, dated February 3, 1892, and routine
  - Pa-Pe, 1963-1974 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Letter to Taft from U.S. Senator John O. Pastore (R.I.) dated March 18, 1974; letters to Taft from U.S. Senator Clairborne Pell (R.I.) dated September 29, 1965 and July 21, 1965 and routine
  - Perlman Article, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Essay entitled "Professor Selig Perlman, An Appreciation" by William Haber, 8 pages, and routine
  - Pi-Pra, 1962-1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Prentice Hall, Inc., 1951 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Pre-Pu, 1962-1970 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Publisher's Receipt Statements, 1948-1965 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Publishers, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Table of contents from Defending Freedom by Taft, 1 page; introduction to Defending Freedom, 8 pages, 4 copies and routine
  - Quarterly Journal of Economics, 1947-1960 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Ra-Re, 1961-1972 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Letter to Taft from Walter H. Reynolds, then Mayor of Providence, dated October 10, 1962
  - Rhode Island, 1947-1971 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Letters to Taft from John O. Pasture, former Governor of Rhode Island, dated January 27, 1947 and May 9. 1949; letters to Taft from Dennis J. Roberts, former Governor of Rhode Island, dated 1/9/52, 1/15/82, and 1/9/57; letter from John A. Notte, Jr., former Governor of Rhode Island dated February 9.1961; copy of statement made by Taft before the Rhode Island Senate Subcommittee on Employment and Manpower, March 3 (no year), 5 pages; letters to Taft from John H. Chafee, former Governor of Rhode Island, dated February 11, 1964 and May 16, 1964; report and recommendations by Taft re the R.F. State Employees Association prepared May 10, 1971, 29 pages
  - Rinehart and Company, 1948-1960 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Includes reports and comments on manuscript by Taft, "Movements for Economic Reform"; requests for permission to quote, and routine
  - Ri, 1964-1976 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    routine correspondence
  - Ro-Ru, 1946-1973 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Sa-Sm, 1952-1976 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Includes letters of recommendation by Taft; correspondence from George P. Schultz, U.S. Secretary of Labor; correspondence with Professor Sumner H. Slichter re "Seventy Years of Life and Labor"; and routine
  - Social Science Research Council, 1948-1965 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Correspondence with Paul Webbink, President SSRC re conference, publication; with Elbridge Sibley, Executive Association SSRC re grant application
  - Sp, 1965-1975 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Correspondence with Lawrence N. Spitz re article on Phil Murray, includes "Outline for an Institute for Continuing Education of Local and Other Leaders of the United Steelworkers of America," 3 pages, and routine
  - Stackpole Co., 1942-1965 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Includes publication agreement, and correspondence re "Economics and Problems of Labor."
  - St-Sw, 1956-1975 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Correspondence with Leon Stein, editor of ILGWU Justice re recommendation for a Guggenheim Fellowship for Stein; includes statement of purpose of "American Labor II," 8 pages; correspondence with Emanuel Stein re publications; correspondence with David Sullivan, President, Building Service Employees International Union, and routine
  - Ta-Te, 1950-1976 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Correspondence with Tamiment Institute re donating Taft's pamphlet collection; correspondence with Teamsters Local 251, Providence, Rhode Island, re Taft supervising election; correspondence with International Brotherhood of Teamsters Fred Englert and Frank Tobin re new structure of the Teamsters Union, and routine
  - Texas, University of, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Correspondence re Taft's appointment as Visiting Professor and routine
  - Th-Tw, 1954-1968 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Correspondence with Penelope H. Thunberg, President's Council of Economic Advisers; correspondence with Twentieth Century Fund re conference and a copy of "Memorandum" on collective Bargaining issues, 1961, 9 pages; correspondence with Gus Tyler, Assistant President, ILGWU
  - United Federation of Teachers, 1969-1974 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Correspondence, bills, notes re study and publication of "United They Teach"; includes a letter, 1/28/74, to Ms. Sylvia Cross, Vice-President, Nash Publications re unauthorized censoring of chapter 9
  - United States Department of Labor, 1951-1971 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Correspondence with Lawrence R. Klein and Henry Lowenstern, Editor, Monthly Labor Review re articles for publication; includes "The Past and Present in the Labor Movement," 14 pages; correspondence with Herbert J. Lahne and Leonard J. Lurie, Office of Labor-Management Policy Development re Taft's manuscript on the evaluation of LMRDA, and routine
  - U.S. Department of Labor - Project, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Correspondence re Taft writing a chapter for the Labor Department's Bicentennial illustrated history of the American Worker
  - U.S. Government - Department of Labor and National Labor Relations Board, 1961-1970 (Box 2, Folder 50-52)
    Correspondence with Arthur J. Goldberg, Secretary of Labor; correspondence re "Voice of America" lecture on "American Labor"; re invitations to speak; correspondence with Ivan Sinclair, Assistant to President Johnson; correspondence with Frank W. McCulloch, Chairman, NLRB; correspondence with W. Willard Wirtz, Secretary of Labor; manuscript (untitled), 11 pages re philosophy of American Labor movement
  - U.S. Maritime Commission, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 52a)
    Letter and attachments re Labor costs in maritime industry
  - U.S. Senate, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    Correspondence with Senator Hubert Humphrey asking Taft to testify on Communist domination of certain unions; correspondence with Senator Winston L. Prouty re labor laws; routine correspondence with Representative John E. Fogarty, Senator Claiborne Pell, Senator John O. Pastore
  - U.S. Steel Corporation and Miscellaneous, 1964-1970 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    Correspondence re proposed study on U.S. Steel labor policies by Taft; correspondence and comments on Taft's "Regulating Union Affairs".
  - University of ..., 1966-1971 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Correspondence with various University Presses re publication of Taft's works; includes reader's reports, and publisher's critiques
  - V, 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Wa, 1959-1971 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    Correspondence with Hedwig Wachenheim and Taft's review of B. J. Widick's "Detroit: City of Violence" manuscript for Wayne State University Press
  - Wayne State University - Dr. Philip P. Mason, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 58)